<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An humble motion made in the time of the reign of Queen Elizabeth, to the honourable lords of her Majesties privie councell, for the reforming of ecclesiasticall discipline and church government after the VVord of God. Wherein is shewed how the livings, profits, and revenewes of the archbishops, lord bishops, and cathedrall churches, may be best ordered and disposed of for the maintenance of an able ministery throughout the land. And the doubts and difficulties which may be objected against that course are fully answered.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86742</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872003</idno>
  <idno type="VID">156956</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240940651</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3421</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E164_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23449</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872003</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99872003e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86742)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156956)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 29:E164[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An humble motion made in the time of the reign of Queen Elizabeth, to the honourable lords of her Majesties privie councell, for the reforming of ecclesiasticall discipline and church government after the VVord of God. Wherein is shewed how the livings, profits, and revenewes of the archbishops, lord bishops, and cathedrall churches, may be best ordered and disposed of for the maintenance of an able ministery throughout the land. And the doubts and difficulties which may be objected against that course are fully answered.</title>
                  <author>Penry, John, 1559-1593, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed 1590. Reprinted 1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed doubtfully to John Perry in BM.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Church of England --  Government.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:156956:1"/>
            <p>AN HUMBLE MOTION Made in the time of the reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> to the Honourable Lords of her Majesties privie Councell, for the reforming of Ecclesiasticall discipline and Church government after the Word of GOD.</p>
            <p>Wherein is shewed how the livings, profits, and revenewes of the Archbishops, Lord Bishops, and Cathedrall Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, may be best ordered and disposed of for the maintenance of an able Ministery throughout the Land.</p>
            <p>And the doubts and difficulties which may be objected against that course are fully answered.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's ornament</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed 1590. reprinted 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="appeal">
            <pb facs="tcp:156956:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:156956:2"/>
            <head>An humble Motion to the Lords of the Councell.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving before by many reasons demonstrated the necessity of reforming the disorders of the Church according to holy Scriptures, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving showed out of the Scriptures what offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Christ hath ordained in his Church, and what Officers, namely, Pastors, Elders, and Deacons; and that Archbishops, Lord Bishops, Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, Commissaries, Archdeacons, Officials, Deanes, Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deanes, Treasurers of Cathedrall Churches, Prebends, Canons, petty Canons, Singing men, Quoristers, Vergers, Curates, and Readers, are but so many disorders in holy offices, none of which Christ gave unto his Church when hee ascended up <note place="margin">Ephes. 4 8.</note> on high: nor are they any of Christs Church-government, but borrowed from Rome, and left as the smoking taile of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrist.</p>
            <p>I am now (Right Honourable) by my humble motion to present further to your wisedomes a way how provision may be made for an able Ministery throughout the Land, and sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of maintenance raised where there is want out of the lands and profits of the aforesaid Bishoprickes and Cathedrals, which I shall doe with all submission, knowing that with far more deepnesse of judgement, and soundnesse of counsell, you are able to inlarge either where it wants, or cut off where it aboundeth.</p>
            <p>Two things in this, I hope, I shall not need to stand upon, that is, first to shew that there are many meane livings for Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters, partly by Impropriations, and partly by the littlenesse <note place="margin">Many meane livings for Ministers.</note> or situation of the Parishes, for this is in the knowledge of all men very clear, that there are divers livings that are not worth above 20. Marks yearly, some 20. pounds, which come nothing neare that competency that were fit for the man of God: who in this last age, not having gifts extraordinary, is driven to stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:156956:3"/> much, and thereby his charges be increased, by buying of bookes, and order of diet, and something for the decency of that calling would be considered in the comelinesse of appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.2.</note> and houshold, that it be not contemptible: and lastly, it is required that he should keepe hospitality; all which, by many degrees, cannot come so low as 20. markes, or 20. pounds, as if we looke upon the proportion of Gods provision under the Law, which the Holy Ghost teacheth to be our pattern, 1 Cor. 9.8, 9, 10, it may appeare: there shall we finde, that for the <note place="margin">Ministers ought to have very good maintenance. Num. 18. &amp; 28</note> maintenance of the Ministery they had not onely the tenths and convenient dwelling places, but even all the first fruits, and of all offerings of divers sorts, and they were bound to three feasts every yeare, (besides every new moone and Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath) wherein every male was to appeare before the Lord, <note place="margin">Deut. 15. &amp; 16 &amp; 12. Levit. 23.</note> but he might not come empty: yet in all these, and many moe charges, they prospered, though it seemed never so charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, so long as they willingly served God after his order. And for so much as our Land, by the blessing of God, may well bee accounted among the fertile and rich soiles of the world, I hope we are not so ungratefull, as to recompence God with a vile and base entertainment of his servants, understanding very well, that it is a small matter that the Minister should reap car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall things of them, upon whom they sow spirituall things. <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The other thing, which I trust I shall not need to stand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is this: that seeing there is need, and that very great, that the Ministery should be better provided for, it were the duty of the Commonwealth to take care that those things (which <note place="margin">The Church livings are to be bestowed on <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters.</note> by their foundation were first meant and ordained for the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God, and have beene, and now are in the opinion of all men bestowed to that use) in the time of reformation should be kept for that very use, that the reforming of things be not thought rather a bait to feed our bellies, then to proceed of any godly zeale, or love or Religion; for who would not think it a plaine mockery of God, and a scorne of godlinesse, that men going about to beautifie the Church, should rob and ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sacke the same? and pretending to further the service of God, should give occasion to prophane it? This were the most di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellish policy in the world, and the onely engine almost to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:156956:3"/> overthrow both Prince and People: For God saith, if men of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer <note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. 1 7. cap. 3.9.</note> the blind and the lame unto a Prince, he would not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, nor accept the person; and shall we thinke that God can put it up at our hands, if the things of his holinesse should bee <note place="margin">2 Cor. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> lightly regarded, and that his ambassadors should bee so spite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully shaven, and their coats cut off to the middle? No, no: he <note place="margin">2 Sam. 10.4. H<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g. 1.9.10.</note> will not take it in good part: for in the zeale of his wrathfull indignation, he pronounceth such men accursed, with a curse, because they have spoiled him, and maketh the heaven over them to stay it selfe from dew, and the earth to stay her fruit, because his house lyeth waste. I hope rather we will hearken unto <hi>Solomon</hi> who saith, Honour the Lord with thy riches, and <note place="margin">Prov. 3 9.</note> with the first fruits of all thine increase: so shall thy barnes be filled with abundance, and thy presses shall burst with new wine. Be it far from us in so clear light of the Gospel, we should be slower in this duty, then our forefathers, who did they knew not what. The matter then I will stand upon, is the thing which may thus be imployed, what it is, and how it is to be ordered: The first point what it is, may partly bee understood by that which is already spoken: for I mean the Archbb. and L. Bb. <note place="margin">Want may se<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve to make suffic<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving for a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ministery in England.</note> livings, and all the Cathedrall churches, houses and lands, and whatsoever profits adjoyned, excepting free schools &amp; almes houses, or such like, which unto some of them belong: The na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of reformation, as may appear by that which is already de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, and the good of our land requireth, that these dignities or spiritual promotions which are not of Gods planting, should be pulled up by the roots, and the men of those places (such as are fit for learning and reverend behaviour) applied and tied to some congregation, where they should labour to feed souls: then would there be many a faire palace void of a master, and goodly houses, churches, and lands void of owners. Here I take it to be the duty of the commonwealth to keepe these livings still for the maintenance of the Ministery, seeing there is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great need of them, and to change only the order and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of applying: that whereas before they served to uphold a lordly pomp, idlenes and bravery in some few: they might now by a wise and godly distribution, be communicated unto many, for the benefit of many Churches. The lands, houses, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:156956:4"/> palaces may be sold, and the money bestowed to the redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Impropriations, and increase of small livings: and surely this is of all other most equall, that where the people doe pay their tenths under the name and propriety of the Churches use, they should be so applyed indeed. And againe, seeing the corruption of our time hath made Impropriations as fee-simple lands, they which have reasonable recompence for the value of them they possesse, should by no meanes thinke themselves injured. It is no reason, that seeing the people doe already stand burdened with such a great charge, that they should bee oppressed with a second, especially when there is a meanes to releeve them. And it is against all conscience that the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery should be left without just and comely provision &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance. But of all other, it were most unwise and ungodly, <note place="margin">Foreslow not the time till the Bishops and Cathedral Prelates have wasted all.</note> to foreslow the occasion, especially when the Commonwealth was never so rich by yearly fruits and commodities. And it is yet more horrible wickednesse, that private men (although peradventure some of them have done service) should prevent the Church, and commit so great sacriledge. For if they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve, there is sufficient besides to reward them. There is no good Christian, or man, either of valour or fortitude, and wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, or of estimation for religion and honesty, or of any good name for justice and clemency, can be of so base and servile a minde, as to grope after the spoile and havocke of the Church, or to suffer himselfe to be rewarded with those goods which <note place="margin">A good man will not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich himselfe with that which should serve to the sole benefit of many. Neh. 5. 10.</note> should by all reason and conscience be imployed to the service and immediate honour of Almighty God. But I hope these speeches shall not need, and that the example of <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> that honourable and zealous Prince, will be followed in this case, he having the feare of God before his eyes, being twelve yeares governour over the people that came from Babel, when his labour was to build the wal<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Ierusalem, and to set up the purity of religion; that hee might give good example to the Princes and Rulers, and that the people might no way be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged, that so the businesse of the Lord might goe chearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and prosperously forward, as it did indeed. Hee not onely tooke nothing to him, which was due unto him, as hee was chiefe Governour, but also spent of that which he had of his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:156956:4"/> owne, for the common charges of the wall, and fed many at his table, lent his mony to the poore, redeemed them that were captive, and caused his servants to doe the like in their place, and that all of them came to helpe forward the worke. The example of <hi>Jehoash</hi> King of Iuda, is very memorable for this <note place="margin">2 King. 12.</note> purpose, when the Priests had neglected the repayring of the decayed places of the Temple (notwithstanding the Kings commandement) till the three and twentieth year of his reign: The charge and money for that businesse was committed to others, who were so far from gaining by it, that they shewed such faithfulnesse in doing of it, that it was not thought need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that they should give any accounts of their doing. If ever it please God to give reformation amongst us, I pray God that this mercy in framing of the hearts of all sorts and degrees, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the good of these examples, may bee also a blessing upon us, as I hope that through his tender compassion and bounty it will.</p>
            <p>Now as great a matter standeth in the second point, how this shall be ordered: one saith that it would be very good that it should be all, and all the other Church-livings likewise taken out of the Ministers hands, and that they should have their severall pensions or stipends of a reasonable sort; for this, saith he, would be easiest and quietest, so that they should bee troubled with nothing but to follow their bookes, and looke to their charge. If it might be so indeed, as these words doe roundly beare us in hand, in very good shew, it were the best, and every Minister would bee glad of the quietest way, and most benefit to the Church. Another peradventure is of a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse <note place="margin">To put all the Ministers to their pensions were not good.</note> minde, and thinketh it very inconvenient, especially at this time, when there is a setled provision for most places, and that by such a meanes as is no great trouble to the Minister, that will not wilfully be a loyterer. It is better to keepe a good way which we have, then to follow a new, and change for the worse: and truly this latter agreeth most with policy for the State, and with benefit for the Church: for the State, it is found a point of tryed policy to alter as few things as may be, (especially when they are good and well) wherein the people have had a long cust<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> interest, for this is a way
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:156956:5"/> unto murmurings, discontentment, stirs and sedition, and the people will quickly suspect, that for the private gaine of some few, such things are invented, when they see plainly that it is very well already. I doubt it will bee found a hard measure to some, an unlucky peece of worke to begin, heavie in the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and a day of blacknesse unto posterity. Secondly, there must be offices erected and augmented, and a great many men must have leases, or some other authority and office to gather the fruits: and what will come of this (which requireth many devices?) a man cannot tell at the first sight, neither shall he see all the mischiefes till it be practised: but this must needs fall out, that many men for gathering the fruits, for receiving and paying againe, must have a fleece, and so the Church shall be shortned and shorne of her right, by a needlesse occupation: when the people shall pay peradventure well the more, for he that hireth must live by it: againe, when the right and proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is out of the Churches hold: it may offer occasion in time, that it shall be taken away altogether, and then there will bee injury to the Church, and oppression of the people.</p>
            <p>But the other is every way better: First, it is easier to bee <note place="margin">The ready way to provide for ministers.</note> done when there remaineth no more but the due examinations of the livings, and to redeeme the impropriations, and to aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the smaller livings: it is without all suspition, for we see the practice, we know it to be good, and need not feare any ill to come of it: and it is more just, for then the whole living go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that way it should, and the people will the better away with it, partly, because they see it is bestowed according to their minde, and partly because they are likely to bee better used, and the minister for his part shall be better able to keepe hospitality, and to seed the poore by the use of such things as arise by that meanes, and that which is no small commodity, he may let out part, or all, as he shall finde most for his ease, and and best for his profit; and if there any benefit arise, this open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the doore to him, whereas the other way penneth him in to one certaine place, be it good or be it bad: and it may bee that his neighbours of good will for his ease, will gather his fruits for him, and he shall save all, that by the other way should be lost, both to him and the people. Briefly, the more one look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:156956:5"/> in the comparison of these two wayes, the more hee shall perceive, that the order now established is the best: if the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriations were redeemed, and the small livings increased. Now for the furthering of this good worke, there are two things to be added, which will helpe this matter very well: First, the uniting of divers little Parishes in one, a thing of <note place="margin">Uniting of <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mall livings one helpe to the ministery.</note> common practice, out of which commeth this commodity, the living is increased, and by the number of the people there are the more wise men to be chosen for Ecclesiasticall officers: and the Church shall be the more comely, and as easily taught in a manner. The next is, there are certaine things scattered <note place="margin">Benefices without cure may be some h<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lpe, united to the smaller livings. Resigning and redeeming of Impropriati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by Bishops and Cath<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dral livings, will be a good meanes to maintaine a learned Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery. Josh. 18.4.</note> here and there without cure, these may be joyned to help the smaller livings.</p>
            <p>Then as touching the impropriations; in some there is great ease, and in some there is no great hardnesse. Those which be in Lord Bishops hands, and pertaining to these great Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, may easily be redeemed, if they bee sent from whence they came there need be no charge: and I doubt not but the third part will be thus redeemed: but if there be any in the Queenes possession, or of any temporall man, or in Colledges, the lands and houses and other temporalties of the Lord Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, and other great Churches, may be imployed to redeeme them: If the consideration and account of these things be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to wise and godly men, inhabiting in every shire, where such livings and Churches are (as <hi>Joshna</hi> appointed three of every Tribe to walke through the Land to describe it) it will easily be found out, that the living of the Ministery will bee brought to a good and comely measure: and that every Church would have at the least two hundred markes yearly for the <note place="margin">Tithe wood, medow, &amp;c. might help in some places. The overplus of Bishops and Cathedrall livings may pay first fruits, tenths, subsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, &amp;c.</note> Pastor and Teacher, and some above two hundred pound, which might also be holpen in some places by tythe wood and meadow, and a greater size of pasture, where such things are either not payd, or not according to the value of the tenths by much.</p>
            <p>But here groweth a question: What if the Lord Bishops and the Cathedrall Churches come to more then will serve for the redeeming of the Impropriations, or lesse? If more, (as I am verily perswaded it will) it may serve to recompence the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:156956:6"/> first fruits and tenths, which were from these Sees and Churches, it may serve to erect in all Shires a Lecture of all Sciences, that such as cannot put their sonnes to Cambridge or Oxford, may have them in the free Schooles, and after by those Lectures brought through all arts: which would greatly increase learned and wise men in this land, and make a flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishing time.</p>
            <p>But if it should fall short of our reckoning, there is yet an <note place="margin">If Bishops and Cathedrall li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings be too little, a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence will make it up. Exod. 36.5.6. Our forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers liberall in g<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ving to the Church.</note> easie helpe, that is, a free benevolence, and as it were an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering of all sorts of people, young and old, through this land: this way hath the Church of God beene very much holpen and advanced; and who is it that will not bee willing to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther such a worthy, honourable, and holy worke? In the time of <hi>Moses,</hi> when he built the Tabernacle, and made the altars and Priests garments, things of a wonderfull great charge, for gold, silver, silke, precious stones, incense, and all costly things, the people came so willingly, and offered so plentifully, that there was too much, so that <hi>Moses</hi> proclaimed that they should offer no more. And when <hi>Hezekiah</hi> commanded to bring a <note place="margin">2 Chro. 31.4.</note> part to the Priests and Levites, to incourage them in the Law, they brought in such abundance, that they did eat and were filled, and yet there remained plenty in heapes that they had made. And in <hi>Davids</hi> time, for the building of the Temple, <note place="margin">1 Chro. 29.6.</note> the Princes of the families, and the Princes of the Tribes of Israel, and the Captaines of thousands, and of hundreds, with the rulers of the Kings worke, offered willingly, and gave for the house of God five thousand talents of gold, and 10000. peeces, and 10000. talents of silver, 18000. talents of brasse, 100000. talents of iron, and they with whom precious stones were found, gave them to the treasure: and the people rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced when they offered willingly, for they offered willingly unto the Lord, with a perfect heart, and <hi>David</hi> the King also rejoyced with great joy. And there is no reason to feare the contrary in our time, of which it is written: <hi>The people shall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 110.3.</note>
               <hi>willingly in the time of the assembly.</hi> I doubt not therefore of Gods mercy and blessing, if we were as forward to goe about such a matter, with singlenesse of heart, and simplicity of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wisedome, and would follow after it with earnestnesse of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:156956:6"/> zeale, and painfulnesse of knowledge, forgetting our owne ease, pleasure, wealth and will, to prefer the true worship of God, the benefit of our soules, the glory of the Gospell of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, unto the praise of God the Father, and this would be the glory of our Land. For thus speaketh God unto his own people, whom he honoureth with his word, <hi>Bring ye all the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 3.10</note>
               <hi>tithes into the storehouse, that there may bee meat in my house, and prove me now herewith, if I will not open the windowes of heaven unto you, saith the Lord of Hosts, if I will not open the windowes of heaven unto you, and poure you out a blessing without measure, and I will rebuke the devourer for your sakes: and hee shall not destroy the fruit of your ground, neither shall your vine be barren in the field, saith the Lord of Hosts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If I should stay here, I might be accused either of unjustice or cruelty; of unjustice, because I have but sleightly spoken of her Majesties due, in the first fruits, tenths, and subsidy of the Clergy (as they call it) and of presentations never a word.</p>
            <p>The first of these is the greatest doubt: for if the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth stand in need (as it is likely in this trouble some time) then there is good reason that all men helpe without any pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge, in as much as every one hath part of the benefit and comfort, otherwise, I am perswaded, that the royall and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian heart of her Majesty would as willingly part from it, and especially the first fruits and tenths, knowing how they came in, as ever <hi>David</hi> did, who considering that it was the house <note place="margin">1 Chron. 29. 3.4.</note> of God, and not man, and because he had a delight in the house of his God; besides the great preparations which hee made of gold, brasse, iron, silver, and precious stones of divers <note place="margin">How first fruits, tenths, and subsidies of B<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>shops and Cathedrall Churches may be paid, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding they be sold to redeeme impropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note> sorts for the Sanctuary, hee gave of his owne three thousand talents of gold of Ophir, and seven thousand talents of fined silver.</p>
            <p>First it may bee seene, whether the overplus of the lands, after the impropriations be redeemed, there be not sufficient to repay the value of so much as the abundance of those first fruits, tenths, and subsidies of the L. Bishops and Cathedrall churches doe amount, which if it doe (as I verily think it will, and spare, if things be handled wisely &amp; with a perfect heart)
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:156956:7"/> then there need no further dealing for recompence: and all <note place="margin">1. By the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> other Churches may be as in times past: but if not, then the foresaid benevolence may stop the gap for the redeeming of <note place="margin">2. By the fore said benevo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lence.</note> the foresaid impropriations, that the lands may remaine to this use of buying out of the said first fruits, which would be a great ease to the Chu<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch, and the burden would not be great, at once to give every man a little of his superfluity, to have a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all benefit for ever: Besides that, the Ministery would be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter able and willing at all times, if need be, to give a benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, to further all necessary purposes, to the ease of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, as a recompence of this kindnesse.</p>
            <p>Besides this, if need be, those livings that be increased by <note place="margin">3. By the ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting those churches whi<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creased.</note> the restored impropriations, or otherwise: may bee set up to higher and greater first fruits, tenths, and subsidies: and where three or foure, lesse or more, be made one, they may follow the rate of so that there need be no diminishing of the treasure of the land by this alteration, except it please her Highnesse of her gracious bounty, upon the tryall of Gods rare blessings towards her and her people, to mitigate some part, as a drinke offering of a sweet smelling sacrifice unto Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God: knowing that he can a thousand manner of wayes send it in againe by other meanes, with greater interest and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease: as it is written, <hi>The liberall person shall have plenty, and he that watereth shall also have raine. He that soweth sparingly, shall</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 11.25. 2 Cor. 9.6 8.</note>
               <hi>reape sparingly, and he that soweth liberally, shall reape also liberally, and God is able to make all graces abound towards you, that ye al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes having all sufficiency in all things, may abound in every good worke. The blessing of the Lord, it maketh rich, and he doth adde no</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 10 22. D<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut. 28.1.3. 5 6.7.12.</note>
               <hi>sorrowes to it.</hi> Againe, <hi>If thou shalt diligently obey the voice of the Lord thy God, blessed shalt thou be in the City, and in the field, in thy ba<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ket, and in thy dough, when thou comest in, and when thou goest out; the Lord shall cause thine enemies that rise against thee, to fall before thy face: they shall come out against thee one way, and flye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee seven wayes, and the Lord shall bring upon thee his good trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, even the heaven to give raine to thy land in due season, and to blesse all the worke of thy hands, and thou shult lend unto many Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and not borrow thy selfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As touching Presentations, it would be a very good and <note place="margin">Of p<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>esenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:156956:7"/> commendable thing, if they were contained in the free gift of Prince and people, to be resigned to every Church, which by the lawes of discipline ought to have their free choice of their Ministers. It will be no losse to the Patrons, except a man will stand upon a dignity. For every man holdeth it Symony for Patrons to take any rewards or gaine, and men are sworne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst it. But if it shall not be thought good so to doe, the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that now is of presenting of able and sufficient Clerkes may remaine, so there be sufficient caution that the Canon of Christ be not broken, the order of his discipline violated, nor the Church whereto he shall be presented, robbed of their right in election. Yet in all these things I prefer not mine own judgement or wisedome, neither doe I set it downe as the judgement of all or many of them that seeke the reformation: but, as I have often said, I submit this my private motion to <note place="margin">An humble caution of the Author.</note> your honourable wisedomes, and to all godly learned men, that if a better and easier way may be found, this may be rejected, onely. I crave that the things and my reasons, first and last, may be rightly weighed, and that if a better cannot be found, this may be wisely considered, and not neglected.</p>
            <p>Now in the second place, it were cruelty (saith some) to put downe these spirituall Lords, and great men of the Church, and to turne them into small livings, but especially to turn out the unfitmen: it were pitty to see them, their wives and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to be put to misery and begging. If a man should make comparison with their doings, what pitty ought there to bee shewed upon them, which justly for breaking Gods comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements are turned out, when there is no pitty shewed to such as stand to Gods truth, and breake onely the traditions of men: <note place="margin">Math. 25. 6.7. 12.13.</note> To the one the Scripture pronounceth woe, and therefore why should they be pittied? To the other, the Scripture joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <note place="margin">2 Cor. 9. 16.</note> in league as it were, pronouncing unto them mercy, and with them against the other, <hi>In vaine doe you worship God, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 15.9.</note>
               <hi>for doctrine the traditions of men;</hi> why should they not bee pittied?</p>
            <p>As touching the Lord Bishops and great Clergy men, which <note place="margin">Haback. 2. 6.</note> have so laden themselves with thick clay, that they have much adoe to get up in the pulpit of God: doe they not know that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:156956:8"/> it is their duty, that they please him who hath chosen them to be his souldiers, not to intangle themselves with the affaires <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.4.</note> of this life, and that they ought for the peace and wealth of the Church, to follow the example of our Lord and Master Christ Iesus, and to have his minde in them, who being God made himselfe of no reputation, and took upon him the forme <note place="margin">Philip. 2.5.</note> of a servant, and was made like unto men, and was found in shape as a man, and humbled himselfe and became obedient unto death, even the death of the Crosse, and hee being rich became poore, that we through his poverty might bee made <note place="margin">2 Cor. 8.9. The Bishops and Ca<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drall Prelates, if they be fit, may be apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to some particular Churches of good living. Iohn 5.44. Philip. 2.21 cap. 3.19.20.</note> rich: Then is it a small matter for them to leave thousands, and be content with their hundreds: and surely I hope so of the men that they will: for God forbid that they should be of that cursed crue of unbeleevers: who they know love the praise of men more then of God: and seeking honour one of another, seeke not the honour that commeth of God alone: or of those unfaithfull stewards, which seeke their owne, and not that which is Christ Iesus: or of those damnable belly-gods whose glory is their shame, and minde earthly things, when all the true Ministers have their conversation in heaven.</p>
            <p>As for the other, which by no meanes can be fitted to bee workmen, and to labour in Gods building and husbandry: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they are worthy of nothing for their presumption and rash entring where they should not, but as unsavoury salt to be <note place="margin">Math. 5.23.</note> cast forth, and trode under foot of men, especially such un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrifts, as being broken from living by their trades, or are thrust out of their untimely occupation of a serviture, do choose as their refuge, and for an easie life to be in the Ministery: yet because the Church is to correct her children to edification, <note place="margin">2 Cor. 13.10.</note> and not destruction, and the law of charity wisheth to do good unto all men, yea unto them that have done us evill; and it may please God by this meanes to give them repentance, it may be a very good thing that these have a stipend for their <note place="margin">Unable Mini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sters being displaced, may have some stocke, or a stipend for their life time.</note> life time, or some stocke to helpe them that are not able to get their living otherwise by their trades: and especially such as being very honest men at the beginning of her Majesties reigne, were drawne in of simplicity, not knowing the great burden of the calling: onely herein they have greatly offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:156956:8"/> that through idlenesse they have not, in all this time attained to any knowledge fit for that calling; and they have beene divers wayes admonished, yet some may be one degree more charitably thought of, because they have so small living, that they are driven to labour and care to make it hold out, being burdened with very many and too heavie pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>And in this point, the honourable and noble care of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, hath purchased his due praise in giving sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends or pensions, for the life time of them that were turned out of the Abbies and Monasteries, which were no more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to be suffered in a Commonwealth, then these Lord Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, and unpreaching Prelacy: and it will be found a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thing, and easier for the Church, a little while to beare the burden of these mens pensions or stockes, then to suffer the Church to be damnified by them for ever: for we see that it is a brood of such a nature that will hardly be weeded out, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept this good way of turning them out together be taken in hand: and while men will looke to doe it by little and little, a time will fall out, that they will waxe too strong, and oppresse the good ministers, as the Canaanites did Israel un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Iabin</hi> twenty yeares. Delay is dangerous, and cursed <note place="margin">Iudg 4.1.2.</note> is hee that doth the worke of the Lord loosely and negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently.</p>
            <p>But what, should I run through every thing? I know your honourable wisedomes can doe a great deale more sufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the consideration, searching, and applying of every thing to his proper place, that God hath raised up at your hands ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry notable men which are endued with gifts: which like unto <hi>Beza<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>el</hi> and <hi>Aholiab,</hi> are filled with an excellent spirit of <note place="margin">Exod 35 30. 34.</note> wisedome and understanding, and knowledge in all the worke of God, and to teach other likewise. Therefore as this is every way the fittest time for such a holy and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable purpose, so I thought I was in conscience to make known that which hath diversly and many times beene advised of in my mind, as it were by an humble motion to bring to your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, that which I hope you cannot be ignorant of: and in some sort to enter you in that, which I trust you are
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:156956:9"/> willing and forward unto, and to draw that out with a coale, as it were rudely, which you by good advice and mature judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, may bring forth and make perfect with great profit, beauty, and glory. And I referre all that I have done unto your honourable, wise, and godly censure, that if I have swerved any thing from the word of God, or good reason, agreeing to the same, it might be rejected, protesting that I meddle not with any mans person, but with the cause, and understand and meane when I reprehend some mens doings in the naming of the persons, onely by the title of their place, the thing which is the ground and occasion of such doings: which being taken away, I suppose the evill of such persons will be purged. And thus in all humblenesse, desiring your Honours, and all wise men, to consider in the feare of God of every thing, without prejudice to the truth, or affection to men or times: from my very soule I commend you to the tuition and government of Almighty God,, and whom from the bottome of my heart, in feare and trembling, I doe pray and beseech, to poure downe the riches of his graces upon us all, in all wisedome and spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall understanding, that we may walke worthy of the Lord, and please him in all things, and namely upon his Anointed and gracious handmaid, <hi>Elizabeth</hi> our deare Soveraigne Lady and Queene, to blesse her with long dayes, and good among us, with daily increase of honour before God and men, and joy of heart in the Holy Ghost: and that we all which are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her, may worship our true and everlasting God, according to his word: in truth, sincerity, and uprightnesse, and live in all faithfull duty to her Majesty, and godly love one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, being blessed with peace, wealth, and godlinesse, from generation to generation, through Iesus Christ our Saviour, to whom with the Father and the Holy Spirit, one God, bee all honour and glory for ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>